<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Neu3CA</title>
    <link>http://95.85.33.21/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Neu3CA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Neu3CA, 2016 </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://95.85.33.21/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Charlotte Germonpré</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/charlotte/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/charlotte/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marijke Miatton</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/marijke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/marijke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robrecht Raedt</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrecht/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrecht/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Veerle de Herdt</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/veerle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/veerle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated cognitive aging</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accelerated-cognitive-aging&#34;&gt;Accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy is not only characterized by seizures, but is also associated with cognitive problems. For example, global cognitive decline is reported in the context of chronic medication-resistant epilepsy, which may indicate a negative effect of accumulative seizures on the brain. However, it is largely unknown what percentage of patients is at risk for decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent interest is focused on the identification of risk factors and characterization of how cognitive functions develop in people with epilepsy. Evidence is found that the cognitive trajectory of patients with epilepsy over time differs from processes of cognitive ageing in healthy people, especially in adulthood-onset epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1889, Gowers introduced the concept of ‘epileptic dementia’. It has been suggested that this type of cognitive deterioration almost exclusively occurs in the context of the childhood-onset chronic (often medication-resistant) epilepsies where accumulation of medication  and seizures over decades leads to gradual decline of the higher cognitive functions. The final cognitive outcome of this ‘chronic accumulation model’ of decline can be similar to the cognitive outcome in some forms of dementia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in daily clinical practice clinicians also encounter another possible form of cognitive decline that is less well described in literature. In a subgroup of adult patients with epilepsy who complain about cognition and a quite sudden inability to meet the demands of daily (working) life, cognitive functioning appears to be globally  deteriorated. These patients do not fulfil the diagnostic criteria of epileptic dementia or a progressive neurological disease such as Alzheimer’s, nor neuropsychologically, nor clinically. The majority of these patients have an adult-onset epilepsy , so that they do not fit into the ‘chronic accumulation model’ of decline either. Cognitive deterioration in this subgroup may be ‘cascadic’ rather than progressive, thus: deterioration takes place in a relatively short period of time, and not as a consequence of chronicity. It these people with epilepsy on which we mainly focus within Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive deterioration in this group develops in a stepwise ‘second hit model’ when epilepsy affects an already vulnerable brain. The model predicts loss of cognitive reserve capacity due to e.g. traumatic brain injury (TBI) or old age leading to a cascade of events after a second hit, i.e. epilepsy. Processes of ageing may be accelerated due to this loss of brain plasticity and cognitive reserve capacity for which we coin the term ‘Accelerated Cognitive Ageing’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/ACAtrajectory.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Graphical representation of Accelerated Cognitive Ageing. The dashed blue line represents the cognitive ageing trajectory without pathology. With increasing age, cognitive functioning is declining until the minimal cognitive threshold is reached. Two alternative cognitive ageing trajectories are shown. The yellow line depicts the cognitive trajectory after one hit (e.g. TBI). There is decline in cognitive function which recovers. Recovery is, however, not complete and results in a loss of functional reserve. This is followed by a normal rate of subsequent ageing. The solid red line represents Accelerated Cognitive Ageing in the second-hit model. After a second hit (e.g. epilepsy), cascadic deterioration takes place and does not recover due to the diminished cognitive reserve capacity. In combination and interaction with the expected changes of normal ageing, cognitive ageing is accelerated and the patient’s cognitive profile resembles that of an older individual. Published in: Breuer et al., 2016&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the concept of accelerated cognitive ageing can be helpful in providing a framework understanding global cognitive deterioration in epilepsy. Moreover due to the cascadic character of the deterioration trajectory (in a short time period) in these patients, it offers a very promising model to study ageing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program is to find specific brain abnormalities for accelerated cognitive aging and to develop treatment options for these patients. Thus, we aim to broaden the scope of epilepsy treatment options from merely seizure management to continuously protecting/preserving cognition. In a broader context, we expect that insights into accelerated cognitive aging are also relevant to understand and slow down healthy cognitive aging in the general population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter de With</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/peter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/peter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Peter de With is professor at the Electrical Engineering department of TU/e and heads the Video Coding and Analysis (VCA) group. He als is Program Director Smart Diagnosis, Strategic Area Health at TU/e and director of the Center for Care &amp;amp; Cure Technologies (C3Te) in Electrical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regina Luttge</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/regina/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/regina/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Luttge studied Applied Sciences in Germany (1989-1993). She had been working as an engineering researcher at Institut für Mikrotechnik in Mainz, Germany, for nearly 5 years prior to starting her PhD studies in Microsystems Technologies at Imperial College in 1999, London, UK. In 2003, Luttge was awarded a PhD from University of London on the development of fabrication technology for micro-optical scanners. Switching her research interest  to microfluidics applications, Luttge had been working for 12 years at University of Twente’s MESA+ Institute for Nanotechnology, The Netherlands, first as a senior scientist and since 2007 as an assistant professor prior to joining TU/e. Based on her established scientific profile in Nanoengineering for Medicine and Biology, Luttge has been appointed associate professor in the Microsystems Group at the Department of Mechanical Engineering in June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is the head of the Brain-on-a-Chip project, which is part of the Organ-on-a-Chip program at the department of Mechanical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rob Rouhl</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrouhl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrouhl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prof Rob Rouhl is a neurologist with a special interest in symptomatic epilepsy (i.e. in which an epileptic focus can be found). He is also interested in treating epilepsy using deep brain stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wytse Wadman</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/wytse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/wytse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wytse Wadman studied experimental physics in Utrecht, Delft, and London, and has a PhD on human motor system control. After post-docs in München, Israel and the USA, he works since 1989 as a professor of Neuroscience at the University of Amsterdam. Since 2005, he is also guest professor at the Faculty of Medicine in Ghent. His research group performs fundamental research of brain processes related to learning and memory, and diseases such as epilpesy, schizophrenia and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease. Besides that, computational models are being developed and collaborations with industrial partners are maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated cognitive aging</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA_old/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA_old/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accelerated-cognitive-aging&#34;&gt;Accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long-standing concern has been whether epilepsy contributes to cognitive decline or so-called ‘epileptic dementia’. Although global cognitive decline is generally reported in the context of chronic refractory epilepsy (i.e. epilepsy that does not respond to medication), it is largely unknown what percentage of patients is at risk for decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent interest is  focused on the identification of risk factors and characterization of aberrant cognitive trajectories in epilepsy. Evidence is found that the cognitive trajectory of patients with epilepsy over time differs from processes of cognitive ageing in healthy people, especially in adulthood-onset epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive deterioration in these patients seems to develop in a ‘second hit model’ and occurs when epilepsy hits on a brain that is already vulnerable or vice versa when comorbid problems develop in a person with epilepsy. Processes of ageing may be accelerated due to loss of brain plasticity and cognitive reserve capacity for which we coin the term ‘accelerated cognitive ageing’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the concept of accelerated cognitive ageing can be helpful in providing a framework understanding global cognitive deterioration in epilepsy. Moreover due to the cascadic character of the deterioration trajectory (in a short time period) in these patients, it offers a very promising model to study ageing&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-mining and graph analysis of EEG data</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/project/EEG_graph_datamining/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/project/EEG_graph_datamining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project, the human brain is represented as a complex network, where brain regions are the nodes of that network and weighted links between each two nodes shows their synchronization and communication frequency. For this purpose, EEG or MEG are used for measuring the activity of different brain regions. For quantifying the relationship between the brain regions, there are a lot of synchronization measures that can be chosen; with the help of those measurements, the functional brain network can be constructed and then modern network science offers a lot of tools to analyze the brain and finding/localizing differences between patients and healthy control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having robustly extracted the network structure from the data, the next step of this project is to combine network theoretical analysis with data mining and machine learning tools, in order to classify and cluster healthy brain connectivity patterns and brain patterns with some disorders. This may be used for sub-categorization of certain diseases (such as epilepsy), which may be relevant to develop tailored treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project relies on knowledge and expertise in signal processing, graph theory, physics and neurology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High field MRI in post-stroke epilepsy</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/project/highFieldPostStroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/project/highFieldPostStroke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;7T post-stroke epilepsy project; description by Rob Rouhl&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview Bert and René</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/post/interview_BA_RB/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/post/interview_BA_RB/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out the image below or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/Neu3CA_ED_04112016.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt; of the interview with &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/member/bert&#34;&gt;Bert&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/member/rene&#34;&gt;René&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/Neu3CA_ED_04112016.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Altered neurotransmitter metabolism in adolescents with high-functioning autism</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/publication/Drenthen_Neurotrans_ASD_oct2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/publication/Drenthen_Neurotrans_ASD_oct2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cognitive deterioration in adult epilepsy: clinical characteristics of Accelerated Cognitive Ageing</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/publication/Breuer_ACA_neuropsy_oct2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/publication/Breuer_ACA_neuropsy_oct2016/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>