<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Project-rsses on Neu3CA</title>
    <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Project-rsses on Neu3CA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Neu3CA, 2016 </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://neu3ca.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time fMRI neurofeedback</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/rtfMRINF/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/rtfMRINF/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special application of &lt;a href=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/background/MRI&#34;&gt;functional MRI&lt;/a&gt; is real-time fMRI neurofeedback (rt-fMRI-NF). In this modality, fMRI is used to access brain activity while the subject is in the scanner, and a certain measure of brain activity is presented back to the subject. The idea is that if a subject is aware of his/her ongoing brain activity, he/she can be trained to influence it. Although not in routine clinical practice, encouraging results have been obtained with rt-fMRI-NF. For example, certain cases of depression are characterized by reduced left amygdala activity. Using rt-fMRI-NF, depressed subjects can be trained to upregulate left amygdala activity, and their clinical symptoms improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below explains our approach towards real-time fMRI analysis and its potential application for neurofeedback:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/eOShxcraaUU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-challenges&#34;&gt;Research challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;a href=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;ca program&lt;/a&gt;  we are investigating rt-fMRI-NF as a way to mitigate cognitive impairment in &lt;a href=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/background/epilepsy&#34;&gt;epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;. Since complex brain functions such as cognition are typically mediated by brain networks (and not single regions), this includes implementing &lt;strong&gt;rt-fMRI-NF for networks&lt;/strong&gt; rather than stand-alone regions. Furthermore, we are looking for &lt;strong&gt;biomarkers of functional network impairment&lt;/strong&gt; that may be exploit for rt-fMRI-NF. Having identified these, they may be used to provide neurofeedback and to study the resulting &lt;strong&gt;changes in functional network organization&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;clinical outcome&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important issue is the &lt;strong&gt;sustainability&lt;/strong&gt; of the effect; how many training sessions are needed in order to have an effect that extends the rt-fMRI-NF session (i.e. also outside the scanner)? And how can these changes be maintained; do subjects need to a new session of rt-fMRI-NF trainings every now and then? At what interval? Or can we maybe prolong the effect using &lt;strong&gt;ambulatory and/or less expensive modalities&lt;/strong&gt; that assess brain activity (EEG neurofeedback, fNIRS neurofeedback)?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data-mining and graph analysis of EEG data</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/EEG_graph_datamining/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/EEG_graph_datamining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project, the human brain is represented as a complex network, where brain regions are the nodes of that network and weighted links between each two nodes shows their synchronization and communication frequency. For this purpose, EEG or MEG are used for measuring the activity of different brain regions. For quantifying the relationship between the brain regions, there are a lot of synchronization measures that can be chosen; with the help of those measurements, the functional brain network can be constructed and then modern network science offers a lot of tools to analyze the brain and finding/localizing differences between patients and healthy control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having robustly extracted the network structure from the data, the next step of this project is to combine network theoretical analysis with data mining and machine learning tools, in order to classify and cluster healthy brain connectivity patterns and brain patterns with some disorders. This may be used for sub-categorization of certain diseases (such as epilepsy), which may be relevant to develop tailored treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project relies on knowledge and expertise in signal processing, graph theory, physics and neurology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>High field MRI in post-stroke epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/highFieldPostStroke/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/highFieldPostStroke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;7T post-stroke epilepsy project; description by Rob Rouhl&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical prospective study of accelerated cognitive ageing</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/clinicalprospectiveACA/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/clinicalprospectiveACA/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text about prospective study in the neuropsychology of ACA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EEG-fMRI coupling</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/EEGfMRI_consequetive/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/EEGfMRI_consequetive/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, we combine fMRI and EEG data to get a more complete view on epileptic networks. We look into the added value of combining the high spatial resolution of fMRI with the high temporal resolution of EEG.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MACA-E</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/MACAe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2016 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/MACAe/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MACA-E stands for &amp;lsquo;MRI study of Accelerated Cognitive Aging in Epilepsy&amp;rsquo;. The notion of accelerated cognitive aging (ACA) as a specific form of cognitive impairment in epilepsy is at the basis of the Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program, but is based on clinical experience rather than systematic investigation. The MACA-E study aims to investigate how prevalent ACA in epilepsy is, and what (specific) brain (network) abnormalities are associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-rationale&#34;&gt;Study rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the MACA-E study is to better characterize ACA in the context of the brain (MRI) and cognitive profile (neuropsychology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;primary-objectives&#34;&gt;Primary Objectives:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we identify neuronal markers of ACA in adult patients with epilepsy on the level of functional connectivity (resting state fMRI), structural connectivity (DTI), structural level (cortical mapping) or blood-brain perfusion?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do these neuronal characteristics/differences in fMRI connectivity correlate with cognitive performance?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can ACA be characterized by a greater loss of cognitive reserve capacity (defined as the change in the first versus the second resting state fMRI, mediated by cognitive activation with a cognitive activation task) , compared to the two control groups?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;secondary-objectives&#34;&gt;Secondary Objectives:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What influence do clinical characteristics (patient characteristics, epilepsy-related factors)
have on neuropsychological and MRI outcome?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-design&#34;&gt;Study design:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;prospective observational study. Multimodal MRI and neuropsychological assessment will be performed at Epilepsy Centre Kempenhaeghe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-population&#34;&gt;Study population:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three cohorts: 20 adult patients with epilepsy and the clinical diagnosis of ACA, 20 age- , education- and type of epilepsy (etiology)-matched adult patients with epilepsy without ACA, 20 age- and education-matched healthy controls, all aged 18 to 80 years, with (premorbid) FSIQ &amp;gt; 70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;main-study-parameters-endpoints&#34;&gt;Main study parameters/endpoints:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cognitive parameters, i.e. the neuropsychological parameters for global cognitive decline (intelligence discrepancy scores, i.e. the discrepancy between the actual IQ and the estimated IQ according to the formula proposed by Schoenberg et al. [3]), information processing speed, attention and memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MRI parameters: macrostructural, microstructural and functional, and blood brain perfusion.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>fMRI and DTI to study TMS in depression</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/advanced_MRI_depression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 16:10:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/advanced_MRI_depression/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the therapeutic potential of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) is investigated for a broad range of neuropsychiatric disorders, up to now rTMS is only FDA approved for the treatment of treatment resistant depression (TRD). Standard stimulation protocol for this patient group consists of daily sessions of rTMS, stimulation frequency 10-18 Hz, repeated for 4-6 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the psychiatry department of the University Hospital Ghent (under supervision of Prof. Baeken), accelerated stimulation protocols are tested in randomized, sham-controlled, double-blinded trials. Accelerated basically means that the stimulation sessions are applied within a couple of days (multiple stimulation sessions a day) instead of over a period of weeks (one stimulation session a day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An MRI protocol, including anatomical, functional, and diffusion sequences, is applied before and after sham and real stimulation. Functional MRI and diffusion MRI data are used to investigate the effects of stimulation on brain network topology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cortical thickness in deteriorating patients with epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/cort_thk_cogn_compl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/cort_thk_cogn_compl/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain cortex contains neuronal cell bodies, at which axons (white matter fibers) end and begin, to facilitate communication with other brain regions. This basically means that a thicker cortex means more cell bodies and more white matter. If these white matter fibers project to specific other cortical regions, consequently the cortex in these connected regions in thicker as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept is employed in cortical thickness connectivity. If certain cortical regions show similar variations in thickness over subjects, they are likely to be connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project we look into specific abnormalities in cortical thickness organization in patients with cognitive deterioration and epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mental speed and flexibility in epilepsy and aging</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/mentalspeedflexaging/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/mentalspeedflexaging/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text about the neuropsychological aspects of mental speed and flexibility in the context of (accelerated) cognitive aging in epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous theta burst stimulation (cTBS) for the treatment of drug-insensitive epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/cTBS/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/cTBS/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epileptic seizure typically originate from an epileptic focus, which is a hyperexcitable region of brain cortex. An interesting treatment may be inhibitory (&amp;lt;1Hz) repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) to tune down local excitability. Theta burst stimulation (TBS) is a relatively novel and potent rTMS protocol holding multiple advantages concerning practicality and durability of the induced effects. This is the first study applying cTBS in the context of epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study, 10 patients with neocortical epilepsy will be treated with cTBS, directed towards the seizure focus. The primary goal is to test the safety and tolerability of cTBS in epilepsy. Therefore, we will perform neuropsychological tests and we keep track of seizure occurrence and other adverse events during the stimulation treatment. Furthermore we are interested in the clinical efficacy. To test this, patients are asked to keep a seizure diary and we record EEG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The secondary goal is to study the mechanism of action of TMS. Before and after the treatment, we test cortical excitability using TMS-EMG and TMS-EEG and we want to study brain connectivities based on high density EEG recordings and MRI (anatomical, functional, and diffusion scans). In other words, we are interested whether &lt;em&gt;locally&lt;/em&gt; applied TMS improves the &lt;em&gt;overall&lt;/em&gt; organization of the brain network.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/TMS_modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/TMS_modeling/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS), an alternating magnetic field is induced in a coil that is held over the scalp, which causes induction currents within the underlying brain tissue. The direct effect local stimulation or inhibition of neurons or more generally, the modulation of local neuronal activity. Since the brain is a network, these effects might also influence neuronal networks and neuronal signalling elsewhere in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this project, we simulate how electro-magnetic fields couple into the brain tissue. These fields are dependent on local tissue morphology (different tissue types, brain sulci and gyri, etc) and thus are highly heterogenous. This means there is quite some local variability in how effectively the neurons are affected. Conversely this also means that slight variations in coil position may have huge effects on the patterns of neuronal activity modulation the induce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having modelled the fields, we are interested in neurophysiology: how is the local neuronal activity modulated, what neuronal subtypes are actually affected, how do these local effects propagate into neuronal (micro)-circuits? We are also interested in how all this is affected by neuroplasticity, i.e. how neurostimulation causes (lasting) changes in brain network organization, and how (ultimately) these network alterations relate to clinical characteristics such as symptom improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;internship-graduation-project-description&#34;&gt;Internship/ Graduation Project Description&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation is a brain stimulation technique that has been used for treatment purposes as well as for diagnostics since the mid nineteen-eighties, but the mechanism of action has not been fully understood. Many questions regarding the extent of the technique, the biochemical interaction between the fields and the neurons and the optimal treatment scheme are yet unanswered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project will focus on one of the many enigmas that still cause debate in the scientific neurostimulation society: Does a low-intensity electric field still influence the firing pattern of a neuron?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer this question, a series of experiments have been conducted in the Cellular and Systems Neurobiology group of the University of Amsterdam. Neurons were stimulated with a repeatable but noisy-looking signal, after which the firing pattern was recorded. An identical stimulation will trigger an identical response, enabling differential testing. So after measuring the firing pattern for the noisy signal, the experiment was repeated, this time while an external electric field was applied. The differences between the firing patterns under various conditions indicate whether and how big the influence of a field on neuronal behavior is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of the experiment described above need to be processed. To verify the conclusions drawn from testing, some models regarding the electric fields, the neuronal responses, and the material parameters need to be set up. This is the main topic of this graduation project (so it is not focused on doing experiments with neurons). The modelling is described in more detail below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;permittivity&#34;&gt;Permittivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While being tested in the ex-vivo set-up, the brain tissue is placed in a solution of salts and glucose. Since the ions are diluted (thus form an interaction with the water), it is impossible to calculate or estimate the dielectric properties (permittivity and conductivity) of the solution. Still, these properties greatly influence the electric field that will be created during the experiments, and thus the (modulation of the) neuronal response. Therefore, they need to be measured in the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/img/field_setup.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this part of the project, a measurement setup needs to be constructed, verified and tested. Next, the dielectric properties of samples of salty water will be tested for various temperatures and frequencies. The information that comes from these experiments will be used to set up the other models of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;electric-field-in-salty-water&#34;&gt;Electric Field in Salty Water&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the experiment, the magnitude of the electric potential is measured at various positions in the water bath in which the brain slice is located. From this information, the electric field vectors are calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/img/Efield_sims.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To verify these measurements, which are somewhat prone to deviations and errors, the experimental setup needs to be rebuilt in an EM simulation environment (preferably CST), so that inaccuracies and confounding factors can be assessed. Note that low-frequency simulations are not as standard as you think, since you often work with potentials rather than with actual fields. Still, this is an interesting part of the project, since you have to combine physics, mathematics and field work (pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;neuronal-simulations&#34;&gt;Neuronal Simulations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there is more clarity about the fields that are active during the experiments, neuronal reactions can be simulated. NEURON is a standard simulation environment well suited for this purpose. You build a simple version of the neuron you wish to study (or, even better, find one in the many databases that are already there), after which you replicate the conditions in the simulation. The responses should be comparable with the responses the neurons generate during the experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/img/NEURON.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part focuses on creating a model that describes the neuronal response to an electric field. Luckily, a lot of information is already available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;furthermore&#34;&gt;Furthermore&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three components described above are all part of your project (in case of an internship, only a subset of the topics will be covered). This, however, does not mean that your project will be restricted to this work only. New ideas, extra side quests, or the possibility to deepen a specific topic can all be discussed and fine-tuned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three topics covered in this project require background knowledge. Supporting information will be provided, and you will have time to get familiar with the ideas and terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;supervision&#34;&gt;Supervision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be supervised by dr. Rob Mestrom and Elles Raaijmakers MSc., both researchers at the EM group at TU/e. You will meet with us on a weekly or biweekly basis, and your progress will be discussed during these meetings. Next to that, a visit to the experimental setup in Amsterdam will be included and extra supervision will be given when working on the permittivity measurements (group house rules for students working in the lab).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have further questions, please feel free to &lt;a href=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/member/elles&#34;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neurodynamics in fMRI and its clinical applications</title>
      <link>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/wavelet/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://neu3ca.github.io/project/wavelet/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-neurodynamics&#34;&gt;Why neurodynamics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) is one of the most powerful brain imaging technique. It allows, in vivo, a visualization at submillimeter scale of brain tissues, and hence, represents a great tool for diagnoses of brain diseases, disorders or impairments. With the emergence of functional MRI (fMRI), not only structures, but also brain activity is assessable. FMRI images can provide insights on the functional brain and its network organization (functional connectivity), and hence deliver new descriptors for brain disorders when brain structures are not impaired. This is particularly interesting in case of cognitive impairments or behavioral  and developmental brain disorders. However, in some pathologies, neither brain morphometry nor its functional connectivity seems to differ when compared with a ‘healthy’ population. This is the case for individuals with autism spectrum disorder (ASD). That is why, over the past decade, neuroscientists have started to investigate the effectiveness of the functional connectivity between nodes of a given functional networks (within the network), or between the networks. But more interestingly, it is the changes in these effective connectivity values that can provide new information over the development of a pathology (such as autism). That is what we describe here as neurodynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-concrete-case&#34;&gt;A concrete case&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to prove the concept that brain dynamics is insightful in understanding a brain disorder and may be helpful for diagnosing it, a framework to assess and compare brain dynamics between two cohorts was built, and showed interesting and clinically relevant results in case of adolescents with ASD. The figure below shows the directed brain dynamic pattern between the ventral stream and executive networks that has a weaker effective connectivity in autism (as compared to controls).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;https://neu3ca.github.io/img/neurodynamics_ASD.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;limitations-and-new-direction&#34;&gt;Limitations and new direction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study on autism uses Granger causality for comparing neurodynamic patterns, and therefore, assumes stationarity in brain signals – which is quite not the brain dynamics realm. Also Granger causality gives us only one value to describe causal-effect between two networks over the full scan length, and hence, loses the time properties of the effective connectivity - when is that causal-effect within or between networks strong or weak?- Therefore, a new direction using wavelet coherence, that allows to describe localized (in time and frequency spaces) correlations between two signals, is currently investigated. Wavelet coherence maps and their localized phase information between two functional networks have already produced great results in case of autism – creation of a wavelet coherence-based classifier for autism is on-going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A multidisciplinary project
Finally, this project is part of Neu3-ca, a multidisciplinary and international research program. Neu3-ca stands for neurodegeneration, neuronal network,  and neuromodulation in epilepsy-induced cognitive ageing. This program aims at looking at the accelerated cognitive ageing phenomenon observed in certain types of epilepsy, its network organization, and the hypothetic  cognitive improvement by neuromodulation (brain stimulation). Therefore, brain dynamics parameters could represent great descriptors of the cognitive decline and the origin of the accelerating process. Neurodynamics are also insightful to help describe or predict possible outcomes of brain stimulation. Finally such fundamental research on brain dynamics could help building a cognitive ageing model, not only in case of brain pathology, but also for the ‘healthy’ population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>