<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Member-rsses on Neu3CA</title>
    <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Member-rsses on Neu3CA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Neu3CA, 2016 </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://95.85.33.21/member/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Charlotte Germonpré</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/charlotte/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/charlotte/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marijke Miatton</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/marijke/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/marijke/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robrecht Raedt</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrecht/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrecht/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Veerle de Herdt</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/veerle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/veerle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Short bio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter de With</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/peter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/peter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Peter de With is professor at the Electrical Engineering department of TU/e and heads the Video Coding and Analysis (VCA) group. He als is Program Director Smart Diagnosis, Strategic Area Health at TU/e and director of the Center for Care &amp;amp; Cure Technologies (C3Te) in Electrical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regina Luttge</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/regina/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/regina/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Luttge studied Applied Sciences in Germany (1989-1993). She had been working as an engineering researcher at Institut für Mikrotechnik in Mainz, Germany, for nearly 5 years prior to starting her PhD studies in Microsystems Technologies at Imperial College in 1999, London, UK. In 2003, Luttge was awarded a PhD from University of London on the development of fabrication technology for micro-optical scanners. Switching her research interest  to microfluidics applications, Luttge had been working for 12 years at University of Twente’s MESA+ Institute for Nanotechnology, The Netherlands, first as a senior scientist and since 2007 as an assistant professor prior to joining TU/e. Based on her established scientific profile in Nanoengineering for Medicine and Biology, Luttge has been appointed associate professor in the Microsystems Group at the Department of Mechanical Engineering in June 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She is the head of the Brain-on-a-Chip project, which is part of the Organ-on-a-Chip program at the department of Mechanical Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rob Rouhl</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrouhl/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/robrouhl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Prof Rob Rouhl is a neurologist with a special interest in symptomatic epilepsy (i.e. in which an epileptic focus can be found). He is also interested in treating epilepsy using deep brain stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wytse Wadman</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/wytse/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/wytse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wytse Wadman studied experimental physics in Utrecht, Delft, and London, and has a PhD on human motor system control. After post-docs in München, Israel and the USA, he works since 1989 as a professor of Neuroscience at the University of Amsterdam. Since 2005, he is also guest professor at the Faculty of Medicine in Ghent. His research group performs fundamental research of brain processes related to learning and memory, and diseases such as epilpesy, schizophrenia and Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease. Besides that, computational models are being developed and collaborations with industrial partners are maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antoine Bernas</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/antoine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/antoine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Antoine Bernas studied Biomedical Technology at Institut Supérieur de l&amp;rsquo;Electronique et du Numerique and did a studies called &amp;ldquo;Génie Electrique&amp;rdquo; at Université de Sherbrooke (2008-2013). He then did a PDEng at TU/e in Healthcare System Design (HSD) and now is a PhD candidate in the field of MRI and brain dynamics at TU/e. Antoine likes to play the drums and has a magnificent French accent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anton Tijhuis</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/antontijhuis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/antontijhuis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Anton G. Tijhuis received the M.Sc. degree in theoretical physics from Utrecht University in 1976 and the Ph.D. degree from the Delft University of Technology in 1987 (cum laude). From 1976&amp;ndash;1986 and 1986&amp;ndash;1993, he has been employed as an assistant and associate professor at the Laboratory of Electromagnetic Research, Faculty of Electrical Engineering, Delft University of Technology. In 1993, he was appointed full professor of Electromagnetics at the Faculty of Electrical Engineering of the Eindhoven University of Technology. He has been a visiting scientist at the Universities of Boulder, Colorado (U.S.A.), Granada (Spain) and Tel Aviv (Israel), and with McDonnell Douglas Research Laboratories, St. Louis, Missouri (U.S.A.). Since 1996, he is a consultant with the T.N.O. Physics and Electronics Laboratory, the Hague, the Netherlands. His research interests are the analytical, numerical and physical aspects of the theory of electromagnetic waves. In particular, he is working on efficient techniques for the computational modeling of electromagnetic fields and their application to detection and synthesis problems from several areas of Electrical Engineering. This includes work on the modeling of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anton de Louw</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/antondelouw/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/antondelouw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr Anton de Louw is a neurologist at Kempenhaeghe and is the medical director of the Academic Centre for Epileptology (ACE), which is a coorperation between Kempenhaeghe, TU/e and Maastricht UMC. He is also involved in clinical research and has a research affiliation at TU/e. Futhermore, Anton is the chair of the Dutch League against Epilepsy. Contrary to medical doctor&amp;rsquo;s code, he drives around in a battered van, but that&amp;rsquo;s because he turned a historic farm into his wife&amp;rsquo;s restaurant.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bert Aldenkamp</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/bert/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/bert/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Professor Aldenkamp graduated in Groningen and was appointed Professor In Leiden in 1991 and in Amsterdam in 1998. Currently he holds the Chair of Epileptology and Neurocognition of Maastricht University Medical Centre (department of Neurology) and is Head of the Epilepsy Imaging Research Group of the Research School Mental Health and Neurosciences (MHeNS) of the University of Maastricht. In addition he is the Head of the Department of Behavioural Research of the Epilepsy centre Kempenhaeghe and vice-chairman of the Scientific Unit of the institute as well as member of the Strategic Board and the Central Management Team. He is currently the supervisor of 20 PhD students and finished more than 100 PhD studies. In addition: Visiting Professor of Epileptology, Universital Hospital Gent (Department of Neurology). Professor Aldenkamp is the Past Editor-in-Chief of the European Journal of Epileptology since 2012 and member of the Editorial Boards of medical journals such as: Epilepsy and Behaviour, Acta Neurologica Scandinavica and Clinical Neurology and neurosurgery. Member of the International Advisory Board of two Pharmaceutical companies. Member of the Dutch advisory Board for two pharmaceutical industries. Professor Aldenkamp has published more than 300 publications (including chapters) and gave about 500 international presentations (h-factor: 51). He owns a Volvo with city brake function (actually private-lease). Since March 2013 he is appointed Professor at the University of Technology in Eindhoven faculty of Electrical Engineering, Signal Processing System group. He focusses on Brain MR-imaging and detailed processing of MR signals especially to understand processes of neurodegeneration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debby Klooster</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/debby/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/debby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Debby Klooster (1988) studied BioMedical Engineering at the Eindhoven University of Technology. During the master program, she went to Melbourne (Australia) for a three month internship in the clinical neurophysiology department headed by Prof. Cook (daily supervisor Dr. Vogrin) and she started to collaborate with Kempenhaeghe. Later she enrolled in a post-master program called Qualified Medical Engineering (PDEng, TU/e and Kempenhaeghe). During this two-year program, her interest in brain stimulation was triggered, mainly by a three month internship in the stimulation lab of Prof. Pascual-Leone in Boston (daily supervisor Dr. Shafi). In 2014, she started a PhD project focusing on the mechanism of action of transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS). The project is a close collaboration between TU/e, Kempenhaeghe and the university hospital Ghent (Belgium) and is supervised by Prof. Aldenkamp en Prof. Boon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Edo Grevers</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/edo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/edo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Edo Grevers obtained a BSc in psychology at the University of Groningen and an MSc in Neurophsychology at the University of Utrecht. He now works as a psychologist at Kempenhaeghe. Did you know Edo literally studied at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Dutch universities that have a name that both refers to a town and a province?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elles Raaijmakers</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/member/elles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 11:45:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/member/elles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My degree is in Electrical Engineering with focal points on computational mathematics and biomedical engineering. My master thesis is about hyperthermia by means of electromagnetic waves, which is a field that is closely related to High Intensity Focused Ultrasound (HIFU). The project included modelling of tissues in the sense of wave propagation and temperature increase as well as designing the antennas of the hyperthermia device. Thus I have some experience in the design and measurement areas, as well as computational and more theoretical sides of the engineering field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a fast learner, broadly oriented and interested in many topics, including science, philosphy, languages and arts. I own a mug with a picture of Gudetama on it. I consider problems a challenge and am willing to dig deeply into a subject to come up with a solution. Because of my many interests, I tend to find creative solutions and combine solutions from a variety of topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My PhD project is about the mechanism of neurostimulation in general and Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in general. I aim to find out which electromagnetic waveforms are most suitable to modulate the activity of neuronal networks, and how varies sub-types of neurons may be selectively stimulated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>