<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Background-rsses on Neu3CA</title>
    <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Background-rsses on Neu3CA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Neu3CA, 2016 </copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://95.85.33.21/background/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated cognitive aging</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accelerated-cognitive-aging&#34;&gt;Accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy is not only characterized by seizures, but is also associated with cognitive problems. For example, global cognitive decline is reported in the context of chronic medication-resistant epilepsy, which may indicate a negative effect of accumulative seizures on the brain. However, it is largely unknown what percentage of patients is at risk for decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent interest is focused on the identification of risk factors and characterization of how cognitive functions develop in people with epilepsy. Evidence is found that the cognitive trajectory of patients with epilepsy over time differs from processes of cognitive ageing in healthy people, especially in adulthood-onset epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1889, Gowers introduced the concept of ‘epileptic dementia’. It has been suggested that this type of cognitive deterioration almost exclusively occurs in the context of the childhood-onset chronic (often medication-resistant) epilepsies where accumulation of medication  and seizures over decades leads to gradual decline of the higher cognitive functions. The final cognitive outcome of this ‘chronic accumulation model’ of decline can be similar to the cognitive outcome in some forms of dementia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in daily clinical practice clinicians also encounter another possible form of cognitive decline that is less well described in literature. In a subgroup of adult patients with epilepsy who complain about cognition and a quite sudden inability to meet the demands of daily (working) life, cognitive functioning appears to be globally  deteriorated. These patients do not fulfil the diagnostic criteria of epileptic dementia or a progressive neurological disease such as Alzheimer’s, nor neuropsychologically, nor clinically. The majority of these patients have an adult-onset epilepsy , so that they do not fit into the ‘chronic accumulation model’ of decline either. Cognitive deterioration in this subgroup may be ‘cascadic’ rather than progressive, thus: deterioration takes place in a relatively short period of time, and not as a consequence of chronicity. It these people with epilepsy on which we mainly focus within Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive deterioration in this group develops in a stepwise ‘second hit model’ when epilepsy affects an already vulnerable brain. The model predicts loss of cognitive reserve capacity due to e.g. traumatic brain injury (TBI) or old age leading to a cascade of events after a second hit, i.e. epilepsy. Processes of ageing may be accelerated due to this loss of brain plasticity and cognitive reserve capacity for which we coin the term ‘Accelerated Cognitive Ageing’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/ACAtrajectory.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Graphical representation of Accelerated Cognitive Ageing. The dashed blue line represents the cognitive ageing trajectory without pathology. With increasing age, cognitive functioning is declining until the minimal cognitive threshold is reached. Two alternative cognitive ageing trajectories are shown. The yellow line depicts the cognitive trajectory after one hit (e.g. TBI). There is decline in cognitive function which recovers. Recovery is, however, not complete and results in a loss of functional reserve. This is followed by a normal rate of subsequent ageing. The solid red line represents Accelerated Cognitive Ageing in the second-hit model. After a second hit (e.g. epilepsy), cascadic deterioration takes place and does not recover due to the diminished cognitive reserve capacity. In combination and interaction with the expected changes of normal ageing, cognitive ageing is accelerated and the patient’s cognitive profile resembles that of an older individual. Published in: Breuer et al., 2016&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the concept of accelerated cognitive ageing can be helpful in providing a framework understanding global cognitive deterioration in epilepsy. Moreover due to the cascadic character of the deterioration trajectory (in a short time period) in these patients, it offers a very promising model to study ageing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of the Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program is to find specific brain abnormalities for accelerated cognitive aging and to develop treatment options for these patients. Thus, we aim to broaden the scope of epilepsy treatment options from merely seizure management to continuously protecting/preserving cognition. In a broader context, we expect that insights into accelerated cognitive aging are also relevant to understand and slow down healthy cognitive aging in the general population.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated cognitive aging</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA_old/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA_old/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accelerated-cognitive-aging&#34;&gt;Accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long-standing concern has been whether epilepsy contributes to cognitive decline or so-called ‘epileptic dementia’. Although global cognitive decline is generally reported in the context of chronic refractory epilepsy (i.e. epilepsy that does not respond to medication), it is largely unknown what percentage of patients is at risk for decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent interest is  focused on the identification of risk factors and characterization of aberrant cognitive trajectories in epilepsy. Evidence is found that the cognitive trajectory of patients with epilepsy over time differs from processes of cognitive ageing in healthy people, especially in adulthood-onset epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive deterioration in these patients seems to develop in a ‘second hit model’ and occurs when epilepsy hits on a brain that is already vulnerable or vice versa when comorbid problems develop in a person with epilepsy. Processes of ageing may be accelerated due to loss of brain plasticity and cognitive reserve capacity for which we coin the term ‘accelerated cognitive ageing’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We believe that the concept of accelerated cognitive ageing can be helpful in providing a framework understanding global cognitive deterioration in epilepsy. Moreover due to the cascadic character of the deterioration trajectory (in a short time period) in these patients, it offers a very promising model to study ageing&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About epilepsy</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;epilepsy&#34;&gt;Epilepsy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy is a neurological disorder that affects 1-2% of the population, and is characterized by recurrent spontaneous seizures and corresponding abnormalities in the electroencephalogram (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electroencephalography&#34;&gt;EEG&lt;/a&gt;). The nature of the seizures may vary greatly, from short spells of freezing and staring in childhood absence epilepsy, to dramatic tonic-clonic seizures in adults, involving falling to the ground and jerking of the limbs. Not only the type of seizures differs greatly between subjects, but also the seizure frequency (from several seizures per day to e.g. one per year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cortical-hyperexcitability&#34;&gt;Cortical hyperexcitability&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epileptic seizures are caused by a problem in the regulation of brain activity; more specifically, an &lt;strong&gt;imbalance between brain excitation and inhibition&lt;/strong&gt;. During a seizure, the brain cortex becomes hyperactive in such a way that normal information processing is temporally disrupted. The nature of the seizure depends on what part of the brain is involved (which area of the brain, and how big it is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;treatments-and-risks&#34;&gt;Treatments and risks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epilepsy may be treated using &lt;strong&gt;anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs)&lt;/strong&gt;, which restore the balance between brain excitation and inhibition (i.e. away from hyperexcitability). In doing so, they may suppress overall brain activity and thus in turn actually &lt;em&gt;cause&lt;/em&gt; cognitive problems. Similarly, epileptic seizures (and ongoing abnormal brain activity in between seizures) may compromise brain function as well. This means that in treating epilepsy using AEDs, in close consultation between doctor and patient, a careful trade-off should be made between sufficient seizure suppression on the one hand, and preservation of brain function and cognition on the other hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every patient achieves sufficient seizure freedom on AEDs. Chances for treatment success actually drop with every next AED that is tried, and are virtually zero already for the 4th drug. Patients for whom drug treatment is unsuccessful may be eligible for &lt;strong&gt;epilepsy surgery&lt;/strong&gt;, in which the part of the brain that triggers the seizures (the so-called epileptic focus) is removed. This procedure is only possible if the epileptic focus can be well identified (e.g. well visible on MR scans), and always holds a risk for damaging surrounding brain tissue, thus compromising brain function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cognitive-comorbidity&#34;&gt;Cognitive comorbidity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taken together, although maybe not broadly known, cognitive problems are an important aspect of epilepsy and concern both the disease itself, as well as its treatment. It is estimated that about half the epilepsy patients suffer from cognitive problems to a certain extent, and this accounts for about half the disease burden. A specific form of cognitive impairment which receives special attention within the Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA&#34;&gt;accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;ca brain research program&lt;/a&gt; aims to better understand how the cognitive problems of epilepsy are caused and how they may be treated or prevented. We think it is &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/aims/aims&#34;&gt;important to gain awareness&lt;/a&gt; of this less well known aspect of epilepsy, since cognitive well-being is essential for societal and job participation as well as for quality-of-life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>General background links</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/background_general/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/background_general/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;general-background&#34;&gt;General background&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the following pages if you&amp;rsquo;d like to learn more about &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA&#34;&gt;accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy&#34;&gt;epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/MRI&#34;&gt;MRI&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks&#34;&gt;neuronal networks&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation&#34;&gt;neuromodulation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Resonance Imaging</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/MRI/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/MRI/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;magnetic-resonance-imaging&#34;&gt;Magnetic Resonance Imaging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MRI&lt;/strong&gt; is short for magnetic resonance imaging. It is a very versatile medical imaging technique that is very popular in neuroscience. It delivers images of exquisite detail, which can be used to study &lt;strong&gt;brain anatomy&lt;/strong&gt;. Furthermore, advanced MRI sequences exist such as &lt;strong&gt;functional MRI (fMRI)&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be used to study brain activity, and &lt;strong&gt;diffusion weighted MRI&lt;/strong&gt;, which can be used to visualize nerve fibers within the brain. Both techniques can be used to study brain connectivity and &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks&#34;&gt;brain networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/task_fMRI.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;strong&gt;task fMRI&lt;/strong&gt;, for example, a subject performs a certain task in the scanner while his/her brain is continuously being scanned (e.g. every 2s). The scanner parameters are tuned to the BOLD contrast (Blood Oxygenation Level Dependent), which means that the MR signal goes up and down in accordance with brain-activity-related changes in blood perfusion. By assessing in which voxels the BOLD signal follows the task design, so-called activation maps can be generated, see the figure above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to know more about how &lt;strong&gt;diffusion-weighted MRI&lt;/strong&gt; can be used to reconstruct nerve fiber pathways in the brain, check out the section on &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks&#34;&gt;brain networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MRI is actually based on a magnetic property of hydrogen nuclei called &lt;strong&gt;nuclear spin&lt;/strong&gt;. Since soft tissue consists largely of water (around 70%), we typically tune into the spin frequency of hydrogen nuclei (H) in water (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O). However, the spin frequency of hydrogen nuclei in other types of molecules is slightly different. This effect is exploited in &lt;strong&gt;MR spectroscopy&lt;/strong&gt;, in which we assess the exact frequency content of the MR signal to find the presence and relative occurance of different &lt;strong&gt;neurotransmitters&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. brain chemicals that mediate the communication between brain cells.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuromodulation</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;neuromodulation&#34;&gt;Neuromodulation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuromodulation involves neurostimulation, i.e. direct or indirect electrical stimulation of brain tissue, and neuromodulation, i.e. other methods to influence brain states (e.g. neurofeedback).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;neurostimulation&#34;&gt;Neurostimulation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A range of neurostimulation modalities exists that are used to either treat neurological or psychiatric diseases, or to modulate brain function for scientific research purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/noninvasive_neurostim.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-invasive neurotimulation modalities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transcranial magnetic stimulation (&lt;strong&gt;TMS&lt;/strong&gt;) and transcranial direct current stimulation (&lt;strong&gt;tDCS&lt;/strong&gt;) are examples of non-invasive brain stimulation techniques. TMS is based on magnetic induction and is applied by a coil that is placed over the scalp. The alternating magnetic field of a TMS coil causes induction currents in the underlying brain tissue, which influence neural information processing. In tDCS, a weak current is sent through the brain using large, spongy, electrodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/invasive_neurostim.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Invasive neurotimulation modalities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these non-invasive neurostimulation methods, also invasive neurostimulation techniques exitst, in which electrodes are placed within the body during a surgical procedure. The best-known invasive neurostimulation modality is deep brain stimulation (&lt;strong&gt;DBS&lt;/strong&gt;), in which an electrode is implanted within the basal ganglia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conventional DBS, the brain is continuously being stimulated. In responsive neurostimulation (&lt;strong&gt;RNS&lt;/strong&gt;), however, the brain is only stimulated when a certain event, e.g. abnormal brain activity, is detected. The stimulation is applied via a pulse generator that is placed under the left clavicle or in the abdominal cavity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vagus nerve stimulation (&lt;strong&gt;VNS&lt;/strong&gt;) and trigeminal nerve stimulation (&lt;strong&gt;TNS&lt;/strong&gt;) are methods to stimulate the brain indirectly, i.e. via a cranial nerve. Both have an invasive and a non-invasive version. In invasive VNS, an electrode is wound around the vagus nerve in the neck, whereas in non-invasive transcutanous (&amp;ldquo;across the skin&amp;rdquo;) VNS (tVNS), an electrode is placed within the ear to stimulate a specific peripheral branch of the vagus nerve. Also the trigeminal nerve can be stimulated invasively by subcutaneously implanted electrodes (&amp;ldquo;under the skin&amp;rdquo;; sTNS) and non-invasively (external, eTNS), using an electrode patch attached to the forehead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mechanisms-of-action&#34;&gt;Mechanisms of action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These various neurostimulation methods don’t work equally well in every subject, and the exact stimulation parameters are typically based on clinical experience rather than an in-depth understanding of how exactly they influence neuronal information processing. Within the Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program, we aim to increase our understanding of the mechanisms of action of neurostimulation to increase their effectiveness (maximum benefit, minimal side effect) and applicability (e.g. improved efficiency of non-invasive versions). Especially the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ugent.be/ge/inwgen/en/research/neurology/lcen.htm&#34;&gt;LCEN3&lt;/a&gt; lab of Ghent University is an important partner here, with a large translational research line, all the way from fundamental animal experiments all the way to daily clinical care for a large group of (mostly) epilepsy patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;real-time-fmri-neurofeedback&#34;&gt;real-time fMRI neurofeedback&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The neuromodulation modality that is mostly studied within our program is &lt;strong&gt;real-time fMRI neurofeedback&lt;/strong&gt;, although we also work on neurofeedback based on functional near-infrared spectroscopy (fNIRS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional MRI is based on the BOLD contrast (blood oxygen level dependent). Effectively this means that if we record a series of fMRI images (e.g. one image every 2 seconds), the gray value of each image element goes up and down in accordance with brain activity-related changes in blood perfusion. Effectively this means that fMRI provides a non-invasive window on brain activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;left&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/rt_fMRI_NF_v2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 500;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real-time fMRI neurofeedback principle: ongoing brain activity is compared to a desired brain activity pattern and the subject receives feedback on to what extent his/her brain activity already resembles this desired brain state.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real-time fMRI neurofeedback, fMRI data is continually acquired and analyzed while the test subject is still in the scanner. A metric of brain activity is then presented to the subject. Thus, this person is made aware of his/her ongoing brain processes and can be trained to modulate them. In depression patients, for example, certain regions of the brain are too low in activity, and rt-fMRI-NF has been used to train these subjects, and symptoms improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the Neu3CA program, we aim to use rt-fMRI-NF to assess and train brain networks that mediate cognition. Having trained a subject using the high spatial precession (resolution) of fMRI, we aim to prolong the training effect with portable neurofeedback modalities, such as fNIRS.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuromodulation</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation_old/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation_old/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;note&#34;&gt;Note&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuromodulation involves neurostimulation, i.e. direct or indirect electrical stimulation of brain tissue, and neuromodulation, which involves other methods to influence brain states (e.g. neurofeedback).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;neurostimulaton&#34;&gt;Neurostimulaton&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurostimulation is the electrical or magnetic stimulation of nerve tissue. This provides a targeted and reversible means to treat brain diseases. Within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA research program&lt;/a&gt;, especially transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) and vagal nerve stimulation (VNS) are studied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TMS, a coil is held over the scalp, which is driven by an alternating current. The resulting magnetic field induces an electric field that influences the membrane potential of the underlying neurons. Depending on the exact stimulation protocol, neuronal excitability can hereby either be increased or decreased.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/TMS.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy&#34;&gt;Epileptic seizures&lt;/a&gt; may be triggered by a patch of overexcitable brain cortex called the epileptic focus. A potential application of TMS is to reduce the excitability of the epileptic focus, with the goal of lowering the changes of having a seizure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though TMS is successfully applied in the clinic, the underlying &lt;strong&gt;neurophysiological mechanisms&lt;/strong&gt; are largely unknown. For example, why do the neurons respond differently to different stimulation frequencies (reduced excitability for pulse repetition frequencies below around 5 Hz, increased excitability above 20 Hz)? And why is TMS more effective in some subjects compared to others?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA brain research program&lt;/a&gt; we investigate several of these questions. For example, we model how TMS exactly couples into the brain, and look into what direct brain effects are triggered where. We also investigate how these local effects may distribute over the brain network using neurophsyiological models of brain networks and information on global &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks&#34;&gt;brain connectivity&lt;/a&gt; derived from functional MRI and/or tractography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, we look into how these stimulations may lead to (transient) changes in brain network organization, and try to link our findings with behavioral/clinical changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VNS&lt;/strong&gt; is a neurostimulation modality in which the vagal nerve is stimulated, which is a cranial nerve that runs through the neck. It provides an indirect means to stimulate the brain, where amongst others it leads to the release of nor-adrenaline in specific brain structures. Nor-adrenaline has seizure-suppresive effects, and thus VNS can be used as an alternative epilepsy treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, also in VNS the exact neurophysiological working mechanism is unknown. Therefore, the effectiveness of VNS in limited (only in &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the patients implanted with a VNS device, seizure reduction is more then 50%). Furthermore, nor-adrenaline also plays a role in neuroplasticity, i.e. the ability of the brain to adapt. VNS may thus potentially also be used to &lt;strong&gt;improve learning&lt;/strong&gt; or otherwise facilitate changes in the brain network. Within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA program&lt;/a&gt;, we look into how VNS exactly influences the brain, and how we may use this knowledge to improve the treatment of seizures and/or to restore cognitive levels in patients with &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy&#34;&gt;epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuronal networks</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/neuronal_networks/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;neuronal-networks&#34;&gt;Neuronal networks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter at what level you look at it, the brain is a network. It consists of specialized groups of brain cells (neurons) that are interconnected. Each brain function is mediated by its own set of regions, and these may be visualized as activation maps in task functional &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/MRI&#34;&gt;MRI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/brain_network_multiscale_square_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if it is not engaged in an explicit task, the brain is active. This is evident from the fact that although it constitutes about 2% of our body weight, at rest the brain accounts for 20% of our oxygen consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, spontaneous fluctuations in resting-state brain activity may be highly synchronous between distributed regions. These sets of regions are called &lt;strong&gt;resting-state networks&lt;/strong&gt;. By comparison to task activation maps, it has been established that these resting-state networks are related to brain function. They thus inform us about the &lt;strong&gt;functional architecture&lt;/strong&gt; of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of resting-state networks are the visual networks, the sensori-motor network, and higher level networks such as the default-mode network. Using &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/MRI&#34;&gt;task-fMRI&lt;/a&gt;, it has been demonstrated that the default-mode network increases in activity in absence of a task, and may represent processes of task preparation, introspection and rumination. Higher integrity (interconnectedness) of the default-mode network has been associated with higher IQ, and abnormalities of this network have been found in several neurological diseases. Within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;ca brain research program&lt;/a&gt;, we aim to find abnormalities in functional networks related to &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/ACA&#34;&gt;cognitive impairments&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/epilepsy&#34;&gt;epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/HARDI_v3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to studying functional networks, i.e. investigating which brain regions show synchronous activity, it is also interesting to study &lt;strong&gt;structural connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. which brain regions are anatomically linked by nerve fibers. To do this, diffusion weighted MRI may be exploited. In this imaging technique, use is made of spontaneous diffusion (movement) of tissue water. In and around nerve fibers, the main direction of diffusion is parallel to the fibers, whereas it is hindered in perpendicular directions. By probing for diffusion in a large number of directions (A in figure above), local fiber directions can be estimated (subfig B), and the course of nerve fibers may be reconstructed in a process called &lt;strong&gt;tractography&lt;/strong&gt; (subfig C).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both functional and structural connectivity may be impaired in pathology such as cognitive problems.   One may test for changes in one or a few connections, but also overall network organization may have changed. To study network topology (instead of separate connections), &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/site/bctnet/&#34;&gt;graph theory&lt;/a&gt; can be applied. This is a set of mathematical tools to derive descriptors of networks, such as modularity, clustering coefficient, and path length. In a range of brain diseases, the clustering coefficient is decreased and the path length (i.e. the number of steps needed to get from one brain region to an arbitrary other brain region) is decreased. Also within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca&#34;&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA brain research program&lt;/a&gt; we exploit graph theory to find abnormalities in network organization for patients with cognitive problems, or to assess the effects of &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neuromodulation&#34;&gt;neuromodulation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA brain research program</title>
      <link>http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 15:50:58 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://95.85.33.21/background/neu3ca/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-neu-sup-3-sup-ca-research-program&#34;&gt;The Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA research program&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neu&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;CA stands for “neurodegeneration, neuronal networks and neuromodulation in epilepsy-induced accelerated cognitive aging”. It is an international and multi-disciplinary research and innovation program that tries to understand how cognition is compromised by epilepsy, and how this may be treated. Our &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/partners/partners&#34;&gt;partners&lt;/a&gt; are both clinical and technical, comprising academics as well as industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&#34;centered&#34; src=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/img/neu3ca_overview.png&#34; alt=&#34;Drawing&#34; style=&#34;width: 1000px;&#34;/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We especially focus on &lt;strong&gt;accelerated cognitive aging&lt;/strong&gt;, which occurs in a subgroup of epilepsy patients. Our findings may be more generally applicable, i.e. to preserve cognitive functioning in the general aging population. Cognitive wellbeing is highly important in our highly dynamic and information-rich society, as well as in the light of trends such as prolonged job participation and a demand for extended self-reliance and extra-mural care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, within Neu3ca we study &lt;strong&gt;brain networks&lt;/strong&gt; using advanced neuroimaging, e.g. functional MRI to study brain activity and diffusion-weighted imaging to visualize nerve pathways within the brain. Thus, we may identify abnormalities in brain connections or brain network organization which are specific to cognitive problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having identified these brain abnormalities, we aim to treat them using a variety of &lt;strong&gt;neuromodulation&lt;/strong&gt; methods, for example transcranial magnetic stimulation (&lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neurostimulation&#34;&gt;TMS&lt;/a&gt;), vagal nerve stimulation (&lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neurostimulation&#34;&gt;VNS&lt;/a&gt;) or &lt;a href=&#34;http://95.85.33.21/background/neurostimulation&#34;&gt;fMRI neurofeedback&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>